<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on </title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Solon Karapanagiotis 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>On statistical reporting in biomedical journals</title>
      <link>/post/stat_reporting/on-statistical-reporting-in-biomedical-journals/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/stat_reporting/on-statistical-reporting-in-biomedical-journals/</guid>
      <description>Poor quality statistical reporting in the biomedical literature is not uncommon. Here is another example by Cirio et al. (2016). The study itself is well planed, executed and reported. The aim was to assess whether heated and humidified high flow gases delivered through nasal cannula (HFNC) improve exercise performance in severe chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) patients. It all started when I show their Fig.1. Here is my attempt to reproduce it</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Importing Flat Files Into R</title>
      <link>/post/importflatfiles/importing-flat-files-into-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/importflatfiles/importing-flat-files-into-r/</guid>
      <description>There are many tutorials for importing data in R focusing on a specific function/package. This one focuses on 3 different packages. In this tutorial you will learn how to import all common formats of flat file data with base R functions and the dedicated readr and data.table packages. I first present these three packages and finish with a comparison table between them.
Task Import a flat file into R: create an R object that contains the data from a flat file.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Plastic waste and disease on coral reefs</title>
      <link>/post/reefs/plastic-waste-and-disease-on-coral-reefs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/reefs/plastic-waste-and-disease-on-coral-reefs/</guid>
      <description>Recently, I came across this very interesting article published in Science about how plastic waste is associated with disease on coral reefs (J. B. Lamb et al. 2018). The main conclusions are
contact with plastic increases the probability of disease,
 the morphological structure of the reefs is associated with the probability of being in contact with plastic with more complex ones being more likely to be affected by plastic,</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Academic: the website designer for Hugo</title>
      <link>/post/getting-started/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/getting-started/</guid>
      <description>Academic is a framework to help you create a beautiful website quickly. Perfect for personal sites, blogs, or business/project sites. Check out the latest demo of what you&amp;rsquo;ll get in less than 10 minutes. Then head on over to the Quick Start guide or take a look at the Release Notes.

Key features:
 Easily manage various content including homepage, blog posts, publications, talks, and projects Extensible via color themes and widgets/plugins Write in Markdown for easy formatting and code highlighting, with LaTeX for mathematical expressions Social/academic network linking, Google Analytics, and Disqus comments Responsive and mobile friendly Simple and refreshing one page design Multilingual and easy to customize  Color Themes Academic is available in different color themes and font themes.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>