<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>puzzle | </title>
    <link>https://solon-karapanagiotis.com/tag/puzzle/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://solon-karapanagiotis.com/tag/puzzle/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>puzzle</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Solon Karapanagiotis 2018-2023</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://solon-karapanagiotis.com/media/icon.png</url>
      <title>puzzle</title>
      <link>https://solon-karapanagiotis.com/tag/puzzle/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title># 134 Puzzle from the New Scientist</title>
      <link>https://solon-karapanagiotis.com/post/new_scientist_puzzle_134/puzzle_134/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://solon-karapanagiotis.com/post/new_scientist_puzzle_134/puzzle_134/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;Another puzzle from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.newscientist.com/&#34;&gt;New Scientist&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.newscientist.com/article/mg25133551-300-puzzle-134-can-you-work-out-which-keyboard-to-hack/&#34;&gt;#134: Can you work out which keyboard to hack?&lt;/a&gt;. It goes as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;James Blond edges along the corridors of the supervillain’s base, and comes to two locked doors, each with a keypad that requires a four-digit code. He will need to get through one of the doors, but there is no time to guess a four-digit code – the number of possible combinations is staggering!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But wait! Some of the buttons on the keypads are visibly worn down, while others look as if they have never been pressed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One door has a keypad with four worn buttons, the other has three. Blond only has time to try one door, and he will have to try all the possible combinations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which of the two keypads will give him fewer combinations to try – the one with four worn buttons, or the one with three?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we are interested in the order of the four numbers, that is all possible &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Permutation&#34;&gt;permutations&lt;/a&gt; of four digits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the door with the four worn buttons (let’s call it Door 1) we can calculate all the permutations as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pick one of the four numbers (there are four choices in this step).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pick one of the remaining three numbers (there are three choices).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pick one of the remaining two numbers (two choices).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stick the last number on the end.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By multiplying these choices together to get our result: &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(4 \times 3 \times 2 (\times 1) = 24\)&lt;/span&gt; possible permutations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The actual formula behind the calculation is &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(n!/(n-r)!\)&lt;/span&gt;, where &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(n\)&lt;/span&gt; is the number of things to choose from,
and we choose &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(r\)&lt;/span&gt; of them, with no repetitions (we need to choose each number only once). For us, &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(n= r= 4\)&lt;/span&gt; since we have &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(n=4\)&lt;/span&gt; digits to choose from and we choose &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(r=4\)&lt;/span&gt; which gives &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(4!/(0!) = 4!/1 = 4 \times 3 \times 2 \times 1 = 24\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The factorial function (symbol: &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(!\)&lt;/span&gt;) just means to multiply a series of descending natural numbers. Example: &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(7! = 7 × 6 × 5 × 4 × 3 × 2 × 1 = 5,040\)&lt;/span&gt;. Note, it is generally agreed that &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(0! = 1\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reasoning for the door with three worn buttons (Door 2) is slightly more involved. First, I introduce the letters &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(A, B\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(C\)&lt;/span&gt; to denote each of the three worn buttons on the keypad- it doesn’t matter which is which. We can arrange the three letters in &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(3!\)&lt;/span&gt; ways. This follows the same reasoning as before. Now, let’s assume the following order&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\({\color{BrickRed}*}, A, *, B, *, C, {\color{BrickRed}*}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where the asterisks indicate positions where the letters can be repeated. For example, if &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(A\)&lt;/span&gt; is repeated then I simply replace the asterisks with &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(A\)&lt;/span&gt;. We then get&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(A, A, B, C\)&lt;/span&gt; (I replaced the first asterisk)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(A, A, B, C\)&lt;/span&gt; (I replaced the second asterisk)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(A, B, A, C\)&lt;/span&gt; (I replaced the third asterisk)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(A, B, C, A\)&lt;/span&gt; (I replaced the fourth asterisk)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note the first two are actually the same. So, in effect, two asterisks (shown in red above) are superfluous. This reduces the positions the letters can be repeated to 2. And since we can repeat any of the 3 letters (&lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(A\)&lt;/span&gt; or &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(B\)&lt;/span&gt; or &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(C\)&lt;/span&gt;), the number of possible permutations is &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(3! \times 2 \times 3 = 36\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence, James should go for Door 1 with the four worn digits as he will need at most 24 attempts compared to 36 attempts for Door 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;update-151021&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Update 15/10/21&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.newscientist.com/article/mg25133564-500-puzzle-135-how-do-you-hit-the-jackpot-on-this-machine/&#34;&gt;solution&lt;/a&gt; from the New Scientist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title># 131 Puzzle from the New Scientist</title>
      <link>https://solon-karapanagiotis.com/post/new_scientist_puzzle_131/puzzle_131/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://solon-karapanagiotis.com/post/new_scientist_puzzle_131/puzzle_131/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;Solution to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.newscientist.com/article/mg25133522-800-puzzle-131-what-is-the-probability-of-winning-this-game-of-chance/#ixzz775sxHixz&#34;&gt;#131 “The Paradise Club”&lt;/a&gt; puzzle from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.newscientist.com/&#34;&gt;New Scientist&lt;/a&gt;. This week (No 3352 - 18 September 2021) the New Scientist posted the following puzzle:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Down at The Paradise Club, Gus and Bart take it in turns to roll a pair of dice. The first person to score his favourite score for two dice wins, which means being treated to a drink by the other (the loser). They each favour a different prime number as a score with two dice and it so happens that their chances of getting their favourite score is the same for each.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is that probability? If Gus goes first what are his chances of being bought a drink?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The maximum score (i.e. sum) when rolling two dice is 12. The prime numbers from 2 (the minimum score) to 12 are&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[2, 3, 5, 7, 11\]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each score can be the result of the following dice combinations&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2: {1, 1}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3: {2, 1}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5: {2, 3}, {4, 1}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;7: {4, 3}, {5, 2}, {6, 1}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;11: {6, 5}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, a score of 2 can only be achieved if both dice are {1, 1} (1 combination in total). A score of 3 can be achieved either with {2, 1} or {1, 2} (2 combinations in total). A score of 5 can be achieved with {2, 3} or {4, 1} or {3, 2} or {1, 4} (4 combinations in total).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The table below shows the total number of combinations for each score&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Score&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Total Combinations&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The puzzle states that the chances of getting their favourite score is the same for Gus and Bart. Since each combination is equiprobable&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; the only scores that result in the same chances are 3 and 11.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we need to find that probability. We can calculate it as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probability = Number of favourable combinations/total number of combinations&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We already know the number of favourable combinations (i.e. the number of combinations that will give the win) - it is 2. There are 2 ways to get a score of 3 or 11 (see table). The total number of combinations is 36. There are 36 possible outcomes when we roll two dice (6 from the first and 6 from the second die).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence, the probability of getting their favourite score is &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(2/36 \text{ or } 1/18\)&lt;/span&gt; and it is the same for both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, we are asked: “If Gus goes first what are his chances of being bought a drink?”
That is, what are his chances of winning? Gus wins if he rolls his favourite score or both Bart and Gus fail - in which case they continue the game. Let W denote the event that Gus wins. The probability of W is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P(W) = P(Gus rolls his favourite score ) + P(both fail)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is usually called the addition rule&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. We already know the first term, the probability of rolling his favourite score is &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(1/18\)&lt;/span&gt;. The second term can be decomposed as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P(both fail) = P(Bart fails and Gus fails) =&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P(Bart fails given that Gus fails) P(Gus fails)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P(Bart fails given that Gus fails) (1 - P(W))&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To go from the first to the second line I used the multiplication rule&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Also, P(Gus fails) = 1 - P(Gus wins) = 1 - P(W). The first term in the last line (P(Bart fails given that Gus fails)) is equal to the probability that Bart fails, which is 1-P(Bart rolls his favourite score) = 1 - 1/18 = 17/18. So rewriting our previous equation we have&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P(W) = P(Gus rolls his favourite score) + P(both fail)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P(W) = P(Gus rolls his favourite score) + P(Bart fails given that Gus fails) (1 - P(W))&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P(W) = 1/18 + 17/18(1 - P(W))&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P(W) = 18/35&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The probability of Gus winning, if he goes first, is 18/35.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;update-270921&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Update 27/09/21&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.newscientist.com/article/mg25133530-900-puzzle-132-can-you-work-out-on-which-day-a-quiz-will-be-given/&#34;&gt;solution&lt;/a&gt; from the New Scientist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have assumed that each die is fair, that is the occurrence of each number is equally likely.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The addition rule states that for two events A and B, the probability that either one or both events occur is P(A or B) = P(A) + P(B) - P(A and B). The last term, P(A and B), is the probability that both events occur. In our case, it is zero because we cannot have a score of 3 and 11 at the same time, they cannot occur together when rolling a pair of dice.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The multiplication rule states that the probability that both events occur is P(A and B) = P(A) P(B given A) or P(B) P(A given B). P(A given B) means the probability that event A occurs given event B has occurred.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Puzzle from the New Scientist</title>
      <link>https://solon-karapanagiotis.com/post/new_scientist_puzzle/puzzle_115/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://solon-karapanagiotis.com/post/new_scientist_puzzle/puzzle_115/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;Attempt to solve &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.newscientist.com/article/mg25033361-300-puzzle-115-can-you-work-out-where-roman-the-robot-will-end-up/&#34;&gt;#115 “A random robot”&lt;/a&gt; puzzle from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.newscientist.com/&#34;&gt;New Scientist&lt;/a&gt;. This week (No 3336 - 29 May 2021) the New Scientist published the following puzzle:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roman the test robot is being given one final roam before being consigned to the scrapheap where he can rust in peace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He has been programmed to make four equal length steps. For his first move, he can travel one step east, west, north or south. Each of his subsequent three steps must be at right angles to the previous move. The direction of each move is selected by a random number generator, with all four possibilities being equally probable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is the chance that Roman will finish where he started?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to solve the puzzle by first plotting how (and whether) Roman can finish where he started (see graph below). To do this, I divided the space based on the 4 cardinal directions he can take in one step.
These are the coloured quadrants in the plot; his Start/Finish position is also given. For example, Roman will be travelling along the purple top-right quadrant if he starts by going either north or east.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, within each quadrant he can travel clockwise or anti-clockwise. This is depicted with the black and grey arrows, respectively. For instance, if he goes north at the first step (purple quadrant) and then by travelling clockwise (black arrow), at right angles, he will finish where he started. Similarly, if he goes east at the first step (purple quadrant) and then by travelling anti-clockwise (grey arrow) he will again finish where he started. In effect, the purple quadrant corresponds to the path:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;north -&amp;gt; east -&amp;gt; south -&amp;gt; west&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;or&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;east -&amp;gt; north -&amp;gt; west -&amp;gt; south&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://solon-karapanagiotis.com/post/new_scientist_puzzle/New_Scientist_Puzzle_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-1-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using the same reasoning, within each quadrant Roman can travel clockwise or anti-clockwise. This gives us 8 different paths (4 quadrants times 2 directions in each one) in total for Roman to start and finish at the same position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we need to calculate the probability of each of those paths. I’ll use the
path:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;north -&amp;gt; east -&amp;gt; south -&amp;gt; west&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;for illustration. For his first move, he can choose any of the four cardinal directions with equal probability. So, the probability he chooses north is 1/4 (i.e. P(north)=1/4). After that, for each subsequent step he can only travel at right angels to the previous move. This limits his choices to two at each subsequent step. In addition, either choice is equally probable (as given by the problem). In this example, after going north, he can only go east or west with equal probability, so P(east) = 1/2. The same is valid of the next two steps. Hence, P(south) = 1/2 and P(west) = 1/2. To find the probability of the entire path we simply need to multiply the individual probabilities of the path. This is, P(path) = P(north) * P(east) * P(south) * P(west) = 1/32.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we have 8 different paths so the total probability that Roman will finish where he started is 8*(1/32)=1/4.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;update-040621&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Update 04/06/21&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, the answer is 1/4, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.newscientist.com/article/mg25033370-700-puzzle-116-can-you-figure-out-all-the-scores-for-the-1991-season/&#34;&gt;see here&lt;/a&gt; for the New Scientist’s solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
